# Michele Piazzai

## Carlos III University of Madrid Department of Business Administration

Calle Madrid 126, 28903 Getafe, ES
 Normante 6.0.23
 +34 916 24 9322
 michele.piazzai@uc3m.es
 https://piazzai.github.io

ORCID: 0000-0001-9676-7422 Web of Science: ABH-6674-2020 Scopus: 56123810600

#### SHORT BIO \_

I am a social scientist interested in organization, strategy, and decision-making, especially in the context of creative industries. In my research, I apply statistical and computational methods to explain how people use concepts and categories to make sense of products, and how product categories, in turn, shape firms' competitive behavior.

#### **ACADEMIC POSITIONS**

•	Assistant Professor of Management, Carlos III University of Madrid	2020-2024
•	Assistant Professor of Innovation, University of Amsterdam	2017-2020

#### **EDUCATION**

EDUCATION		
2018		
2018		
2015		
2012		
2012		
2011		

#### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS \_

- Michele Piazzai, Min Liu, and Martina Montauti (2024). Cognitive economy and product categorization. *Organization Science*. https://doi.org/10.1287/orsc.2021.15751
- Michele Piazzai and Nachoem Wijnberg (2019). Product proliferation, complexity, and deterrence to imitation in differentiated-product oligopolies. *Strategic Management Journal* 40(6), 945–958. https://doi.org/10.1002/smj.3002

#### OTHER PUBLICATIONS \_

- Angelo Tomaselli, Oguz Acar, Michele Piazzai, and Nachoem Wijnberg (2024). When
  more is more. *California Management Review Insights*. https://cmr.berkeley.edu/2024/
  04/when-more-is-more
- Michele Piazzai and Marilena Vecco (2020). Deaccessioning. *Oxford Bibliographies in Anthropology*. https://doi.org/10.1093/obo/9780199766567-0246
- Min Liu, Martina Montauti, and Michele Piazzai (2018). Old at heart, young at the periphery: An age-dependence approach to resource partitioning. *Academy of Management Best Papers Proceedings* 2018(1), 11589. https://doi.org/10.5465/AMBPP.2018.31
- Marilena Vecco, Andrej Srakar, and Michele Piazzai (2017). Visitor attitudes toward deaccessioning in Italian public museums: An econometric analysis. *Poetics* 63, 33–46. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.poetic.2017.05.001
- Willem Conradie, Sabine Frittella, Alessandra Palmigiano, Michele Piazzai, Apostolos Tzimoulis, and Nachoem Wijnberg (2017). Toward an epistemic-logical theory of categorization. *Theoretical Aspects of Rationality and Knowledge*. EPTCS 251, 167–186 (Open Publishing Association). https://doi.org/10.4204/eptcs.251.12

- Michele Piazzai and Nachoem Wijnberg (2017). Diversification, proliferation, and firm performance in the US music industry. **Academy of Management Best Papers Proceedings** 2017(1), 16528. https://doi.org/10.5465/AMBPP.2017.29
- Willem Conradie, Sabine Frittella, Alessandra Palmigiano, Michele Piazzai, Apostolos Tzimoulis, and Nachoem Wijnberg (2016). Categories: How I learned to stop worrying and love two sorts. *Logic, Language, Information, and Computation*. LNCS 9803, 145–164 (Springer). https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-52921-8\_10
- Marilena Vecco and Michele Piazzai (2015). Deaccessioning of museum collections: What do we know and where do we stand in Europe? *Journal of Cultural Heritage* 16(2), 221–227. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.culher.2014.03.007

COURSES TAUGHT	
Carlos III University of Madrid	
<ul><li>Organizational Design (coordinator), BSc</li><li>Strategic Management, PhD</li></ul>	2020–2024 2020–2022
University of Amsterdam	
<ul> <li>Thesis Proposal Workshop (coordinator), BSc/MSc</li> <li>Innovation Management (coordinator), BSc</li> <li>Cases in Creative Entrepreneurship, MSc</li> <li>Cultural Entrepreneurship and Innovation, MSc</li> <li>Strategic Management and Marketing in the Creative Industries, MSc</li> <li>Delft University of Technology</li> <li>Formal Methods for Strategic Decision-making (TA), BSc</li> </ul>	2019–2020 2018–2020 2017–2019 2015–2019 2015–2017
<ul> <li>Integration Economics, Law, Philosophy, and Technology (TA), BSc</li> <li>Ethics and Engineering (TA), MSc</li> </ul>	2015–2016 2014–2017
INVITED SEMINARS	
<ul> <li>Strategy Group, University of Edinburgh</li> <li>Department of Logic, History, and Philosophy of Science, UNED Madrid</li> <li>Strategy and International Business Group, University of Warwick</li> <li>Department of Business Administration, Carlos III University of Madrid</li> <li>Strategy and Entrepreneurship Group, NOVA University of Lisbon</li> <li>Strategy Group, IE University</li> <li>School of Business, Maynooth University</li> <li>Department of Mathematics and Computer Science, Chapman University</li> <li>Cultural Sociology Group, University of Amsterdam</li> <li>Management and Marketing Group, Durham University</li> <li>Entrepreneurship and Innovation Section, University of Amsterdam</li> </ul>	2024 2023 2020 2019 2019 2019 2019 2018 2017 2017
CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS	
<ul> <li>EGOS Colloquium, University of Milano-Bicocca</li> <li>Nagymaros Conference, University of Amsterdam</li> <li>Nagymaros Conference, Zoom</li> <li>Nagymaros Conference, Zoom</li> <li>Nagymaros Conference, Stanford University</li> <li>AOM Annual Meeting, Boston</li> <li>Nagymaros Conference, University of Cambridge</li> <li>Applied Logic Workshop, Delft University of Technology</li> <li>SMS International Conference, Houston</li> <li>AOM Annual Meeting, Atlanta</li> </ul>	2024 2023 2021 2020 2019 2019 2018 2018 2017 2017

<ul> <li>Nagymaros Conference, Carlos III University of Madrid</li> <li>Creative Industries Research Seminar, Free University Amsterdam</li> <li>Logic and Algebra Workshop, University of Johannesburg</li> <li>International Workshop on Logic and Cognition, Sun Yat-sen University</li> <li>AOM Annual Meeting, Anaheim</li> <li>EGOS Colloquium, Federico II University of Naples</li> <li>Lorentz Workshop, Leiden University</li> <li>Logic and Algebra Workshop, University of Johannesburg</li> <li>Logic and Algebra Workshop, University of Johannesburg</li> <li>EGOS Colloquium, American College of Greece</li> <li>EGOS Colloquium, Erasmus University Rotterdam</li> <li>IASPM Conference, Erasmus University Rotterdam</li> <li>Music Matters Masterclass, Tilburg University</li> </ul>	2017 2017 2017 2016 2016 2016 2016 2015 2015 2014 2014
RESEARCH VISITS	
<ul> <li>Department of Economics and Business, Pompeu Fabra University</li> <li>Department of Mathematics and Computer Science, Chapman University</li> <li>Department of Pure and Applied Mathematics, University of Johannesburg</li> <li>Graduate School of Business, Stanford University</li> <li>Department of Pure and Applied Mathematics, University of Johannesburg</li> <li>Department of Pure and Applied Mathematics, University of Johannesburg</li> <li>Department of Arts and Culture Studies, Erasmus University Rotterdam</li> </ul>	2016 2016
AWARDS AND GRANTS	
<ul> <li>UC3M Business Teaching Award, Carlos III University of Madrid</li> <li>UC3M Business Teaching Award, Carlos III University of Madrid</li> <li>UC3M Business Teaching Award, Carlos III University of Madrid</li> <li>Ramón y Cajal Fellowship, Spanish Ministry of Science</li> <li>Knowledge Generation Project (co-applicant), Spanish Ministry of Science</li> <li>Departmental Scholar Award, Sierra Nevada College</li> <li>Undergraduate scholarship, Sierra Nevada College</li> <li>Undergraduate scholarship, National Italian American Foundation</li> </ul>	2023 2022 2021 2021 2020 2011 2010 2009
SERVICE	
Departmental activities	
<ul> <li>Strategic Funding Group, Carlos III University of Madrid</li> <li>Business Administration Program Committee, University of Amsterdam</li> </ul>	2023–2024 2018–2019
Conference organization	
<ul><li>Co-organizer, Nagymaros Conference</li><li>Scientific Committee, Nagymaros Conference</li><li>Organizer, Applied Logic Workshop</li></ul>	2024 2020 2018
Societies	
Webmaster, Nagymaros Group	2023-2024
Peer reviews	
<ul> <li>AOM Annual Meeting (3)</li> <li>Management Science (1)</li> <li>Organization Science (2)</li> <li>Organization Studies (1)</li> <li>Strategy Science (1)</li> </ul>	

### **OPEN-SOURCE PROJECTS**

<ul> <li>hacked-jekyll, https://rubygems.org/gems/hacked-jekyll</li> </ul>	2023-2024
<ul> <li>jekyll-nagymaros, https://rubygems.org/gems/jekyll-nagymaros</li> </ul>	2023-2024
<ul> <li>opencolor, https://ctan.org/pkg/opencolor</li> </ul>	2022-2024
<ul><li>uvaletter, https://ctan.org/pkg/uvaletter</li></ul>	2022-2024
<ul> <li>arguelles, https://ctan.org/pkg/beamertheme-arguelles</li> </ul>	2020-2024
<ul><li>cvless, https://rubygems.org/gems/cvless</li></ul>	2020-2024

## LANGUAGES \_\_

• Natural: Italian, English, Spanish

• Scripting: Bash, Python

Web: HTML, CSS, JavaScriptData: R, Stata, SQL, VBA

• Typesetting: LATEX